Learning-SICP 学习小组
倾情制作
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
翻译&&时间轴
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
压制&&特效
邓雄飞
（Dysprosium）
校对
邓雄飞
特别感谢
裘宗燕教授
逻辑式程序设计 II
PROFESSOR: All right, well, we've seen how the query language works.
我们已经了解了查询语言的使用方式
Now, let's talk about how it's implemented.
现在该来讨论如何实现了
You already pretty much can guess
你们也应该能够猜到
what's going on there.
它其中的原理了
At the bottom of it, there's a pattern matcher.
它的最底层是一个模式匹配器
And we looked at a pattern matcher
我们在《基于规则的控制语言》一课中
when we did the rule-based control language.
已经介绍过模式匹配器了
Just to remind you, here are some sample patterns.
我举个例子来让你们温习一下
This is a pattern that will match
这个模式会匹配
any list of three things
一个含有三个元素的表
which the first is a
其中 首元素为A
the second is c
其次是C
and the middle one can be anything.
而中间可以为任意元素
So in this little pattern-matching syntax,
所以在这个小型的模式匹配语言中
there's only one distinction you make.
你只能区分一种类型
There's either literal things or variables,
也就是区分字面量或者变量
and variables begin with question mark.
以问号开头的就是变量
So this matches any list of three things
因此这个模式会匹配任意的三元表
of which the first is a and the second is c.
只要它的首元素为A 而第三个元素为C
This one matches any list of three things
而这个模式匹配的三元表
of which the first is the symbol job.
它的首元素必须是符号'JOB
The second can be anything.
第二个元素为任意值
And the third is a list of two things
第三个元素必须是一个二元表
of which the first is the symbol computer
二元表的首元素为符号'COMPUTER
and the second can be anything.
第二个元素可以为任意值
And this one, this next one matches any list of three things,
而下一条模式所匹配的三元表
and the only difference is,
区别就在于
here, the third list, the first is the symbol computer,
在于第三个元素的首元素必须为符号'COMPUTER
and then there's some rest of the list.
表剩余部分可以是任意值
So this means two elements and this means arbitrary number.
也就是说 上面是二元表 而下面没有限定数目
And our language implementation isn't
然而我们的语言实现
isn't even going to have to worry about implementing this dot
根本不用操心如何去实现这个点号
because that's automatically done by Lisp's reader.
因为这个由Lisp读取器自动地完成
Remember matchers also have some consistency in them.
要注意 匹配器还要保持一致性
This match is a list of three things
这个模式匹配一个三元表
of which the first is a.
表的首元素是A
And the second and third can be anything,
而第二个元素和第三个元素可以是任意值
but they have to be the same thing.
但它们必须是相同的
They're both called x.
它们都是?X
And this matches a list of four things
而这个模式匹配一个四元表
of which the first is the fourth
其中第一个元素与第四个元素相同
and the second is the same as the third.
而第二个元素与第三个元素相同
And this last one matches any list that begins with a.
最后一个模式匹配以A开头的任意表
The first thing is a,
以A开头
and the rest can be anything.
余下的可以是任意值
So that's just a review of pattern matcher syntax
这是对我们已经学习过的模式匹配语言
that you've already seen.
的一个回顾
And remember,
还记得吗
that's implemented by some procedure called match.
这是由一个叫做MATCH的过程实现的
And match takes a pattern and some data and a dictionary.
MATCH有三个参数：PAT、DATA以及DICTIONARY
And match asks the question
MATCH考虑的是
is there any way to match this pattern against this data object
利用给定DICTIONAY中的绑定
subject to the bindings that are already in this dictionary?
能够找到一种方法把模式与数据对象匹配起来吗？
So, for instance,
比如说
if we're going to match the pattern x, y, y, x
如果我们想要把模式(?X ?Y ?Y ?X)
against the data a, b, b, a
与数据对象(A B B A)相匹配
subject to a dictionary, that says x equals a.
又给定了一个字典 X=A
Then the matcher would say, yes, that's consistent.
MATCH就会说：“它们是一致的”
These match, and it's consistent
再给定的字典说 X=A 的情况下
with what's in the dictionary to say that x equals a.
模式与数据相匹配
And the result of the match
而匹配的结果则是
is the extended dictionary
一个扩展了的词典
that says x equals a and y equals b.
其中包含 X=A Y=B
So a matcher takes in pattern data dictionary,
MATCH接收模式、数据以及字典
puts out an extended dictionary if it matches,
如果成功匹配就输出一个扩展后的词典
or if it doesn't match, says that it fails.
否则就报错
So, for example,
因此 比如说
if I use the same pattern here,
如果我在这里使用同样的模式
if I say this x, y, y, x
如果我用模式(?X ?Y ?Y ?X)
match a, b, b, a
去匹配(A B B A)
with the dictionary y equals a,
并给定词典 Y=A
then the matcher would put out fail.
那么MATCH就会输出FAIL
Well, you've already seen the code for a pattern matcher
你们已经见过模式匹配器的代码了
so I'm not going to go over it,
我就不会再去细讲
but it's the same thing we've been doing before.
这跟我们以前做的类似
You saw that in the system on rule-based control.
我们在《基于规则的系统》中已经见过了
It's essentially the same matcher.
基本上是同样的匹配器
In fact, I think the syntax is a little bit simpler
实际上 我认为这里的语法还更简单一点
because we're not worrying about
因为我们不用去关心
arbitrary constants and expressions and things.
任意变量、任意表达式之类的东西
There's just variables and constants.
这里面只区分变量和常量
OK, well, given that,
那么 有了模式匹配器以后
what's a primitive query?
基本查询又是怎么样的呢？
Primitive query is going to be a rather complicated thing.
基本查询将会是一个相当复杂的东西
It's going to be-- let's think about the query job of x is d dot y.
就拿查询(JOB ?X (?D . ?Y))来说
That's a query we might type in.
我们可能会输入这样的查询
That's going to be implemented in the system.
这又将如何在系统内实现呢？
We'll think of it as this little box.
我们可以把它想做这个小盒子
Here's the primitive query.
这是一条基本查询
What this little box is going to do
这个小盒子将会
is take in two streams and put out a stream.
以两条流作为输入
and put out a stream.
并输出一条流
So the shape of a primitive query
因此一条基本查询的形状
is that it's a thing where two streams come in
就将是有两条输入流
and one stream goes out.
和一条输出流
What these streams are going to be is down here is the database.
而这些流 来自于这里的数据库
So we imagine all the things in the database
因此我们把数据库中的所有数据
sort of sitting there in a stream
想象成一条流
and this thing sucks on them.
而这个盒子不断地吸取
So what are some things that might be in the database?
那么 数据库中有什么呢？
Oh, job of Alyssa is something
首先是(JOB (ALYSSA ...))
and some other job is something.
以及还有其它的JOB数据
So imagine all of the facts in the database sitting there in the stream.
想象一下 数据库中的所有事实都在这条流中
That's what comes in here.
都到了这里
What comes in here
而这条流送来的
is a stream of dictionaries.
是一些字典
So one particular dictionary might say
其中一个就可能是
might say y equals programmer.
Y=PROG
Now, what the query does
现在 查询工作就是要
when it gets in a dictionary from this stream,
当它从这条流中取得一个字典后
it finds all possible ways of matching the query
它会搜寻数据库中的东西
against whatever is coming in from the database.
来尽可能产生所有匹配结果
It looks at the query as a pattern,
它把查询视作一种模式
matches it against any fact from the database
并将它们与数据库中的事实匹配起来
or all possible ways of finding and matching the database
结合着相应的字典中的数据
with respect to this dictionary that's coming in.
找到数据库中所有匹配的结果
So for each fact in the database,
所以针对数据库中的每条事实
it calls the matcher using the pattern, fact, and dictionary.
它都会调用(MATCH PAT FACT DICTIONAY)来检查
And every time it gets a good match,
如果成功匹配
it puts out the extended dictionary.
它就输出一个扩展了的字典
So, for example, if this one comes in
比如说 这里进来了一本字典
and it finds a match,
并且成功匹配
out will come a dictionary
那么就会输出一本字典
that in this case will have y equals programmer
本例中就是Y=PROG
nd x equals something.
X=...
y is programmer, x is something,
Y=PROG X=...
and d is whatever it found.
D又是一个新的项
And that's all.
像这样扩展
And, of course, it's going to try this for every fact in the dictionary.
当然 它会针对数据库中的所有事实做同样的尝试
So it might find lots of them.
所以就可能有很多的结果
It might find another one
可能会产生另一本字典
that says y equals programmer and x equals, and d equals.
其中 Y=PROG X=... D=...
So thats, So for one frame coming in,
因此 对于每个输入的框架
it might put out-- for one dictionary coming in,
对于每输入一本字典
it might put out a lot of dictionaries,
它可能输出很多本字典
or it might put out none.
或者什么也不输出
It might have something that wouldn't match like x equals FOO.
可能会有一些不匹配的情况 比如X=FOO
This one might not match anything
这个条目不会匹配任何东西
in which case nothing will go into this stream corresponding to this frame.
就这个框架来说 不会向输出流中输出东西
Or what you might do is put in an empty frame,
或者你也可以输入一个空框架
and an empty frame says try matching all ways--
空框架是用来
find all possible ways of matching the query
在没有任何约束的情况下
against something in the database subject to no previous restrictions.
匹配数据库中所有可能的结果
And if you think about what that means, that's just
这仅仅代表着
the computation that's done when you type in a query right off.
处理你输入的查询 最初所进行的计算
It tries to find all matches.
它试图找出所有的匹配
So a primitive query sets up this mechanism.
基本查询建立了这种机制
And what the language does,
而语言要做的是
when you type in the query at the top level,
当你在顶层输入这条查询时
it takes this mechanism,
它基于这种机制
feeds in one single empty dictionary,
它会输入一本空的字典
and then for each thing that comes out
而对于输出的每个东西
takes the original query
然后把最初的查询
and instantiates the result with all the different dictionaries,
用不同的字典来实例化
producing a new stream of instantiated patterns here.
于是实例化后的模式就形成了一条新的流
And that's what gets printed on the terminal.
这就是在终端上打印出来的内容
That's the basic mechanism going on there.
这也就是其中的基本原理
Well, why is that so complicated?
那么 这又为什么复杂呢？
You probably can think of a lot simpler ways to arrange this match for
除了使用这种基于流的方法
a primitive query rather than having all of these streams floating around.
你们可以想出很多更简单的方法来组织基本查询
And the answer is--
而答案就在于
you probably guess already.
你们可能已经在想了
The answer is this thing extends elegantly
答案就是 这种方法能够优雅地
to implement the means of combination.
实现组合手段
So, for instance,
比如说
suppose I don't only want to do this.
假设我还想实现其它的效果
I don't want to say who to be everybody's job description.
我不只是想查询所有人的工作信息
Suppose I want to say
假设我还想查询
to say AND the job of x is d dot y
(AND (JOB ?X (?D . ?Y))
and the supervisor of x is z.
(SUPERVIOSR ?X ?Z))
Now, supervisor of x is z
(SUPERVISOR ?X ?Z)这条查询
is going to be another primitive query
是另外的一条基本查询
that has the same shape to take in a stream of data objects,
它也有类似的形状——接收一条数据对象流
a stream of initial dictionaries,
一条初始字典流
which are the restrictions to try and use when you match,
字典是你在进行匹配时 需要遵循的约束
and it's going to put out a stream of dictionaries.
然后它会输出一条字典流
So that's what this primitive query looks like.
这就是这条基本查询的形状
And how do I implement the AND?
我又该如何实现AND呢？
Well, it's simple.
其实很简单
I just hook them together.
把它们连接起来就好了
I take the output of this one,
我把这条查询的输出
and I put that to the input of that one.
连接在这条查询的输入上
And I take the dictionary here and I fan it out.
然后把这里的字典扇出开来
And then you see how that's going to work,
你们就能发现它是如何工作的了
because what's going to happen is a frame will now come in here,
这里会输出一个框架
which has a binding for x, y, and d.
其中有X、Y和D的绑定
And then when this one gets it, it'll say,
当后面的查询接收到结果后
oh, gee, subject to these restrictions,
当它了解了这些约束后
which now already have values in the dictionary for y and x and d,
字典中的是Y、X和D的值
it looks in the database and says,
它会搜寻数据库
gee, can I find any supervisor facts?
试图找到有关SUPERVISOR关系的事实
And if it finds any, out will come dictionaries
如果找到了的话 它就会输出一些词典
which have bindings for y and x and d and z now.
其中有Y、X、D以及Z的绑定
And then notice that the match---
不过要注意
because the frames coming in here have these restrictions,
因为这里输入的框架建立了约束
that's the thing that assures when you do the AND,
它保证了当你执行AND运算时
this x will mean the same thing as that x.
这两个X是相同的
Because by the time something comes floating in here,
这是因为通过这条流输出时
x has a value that you have to match against consistently.
X已经有值了 你要确保匹配的一致性
And then you remember from the code from the matcher,
然后我们想起在MATCH的代码中
there was something in the way the matcher did dictionaries
有一种操作字典的特殊组织方法
that arrange consistent matches.
确保了匹配的一致性
So there's AND.
这就是AND的实现
The important point to notice is the general shape.
关键是要注意它的一般性形状
Look at what happened: the AND of two queries, say, P and Q.
我们来看看(AND P Q)
Here's P and Q.
这里是P和Q
The AND of two queries,
两条查询的AND
well, it looks like this.
看起来像是这样
Each query takes in a stream from the database,
每一条查询都通过一条流连接数据库
a stream of inputs,
一条输入流
and puts out a stream of outputs.
并输出一条输出流
And the important point to notice
关键是要注意
is that if I draw a box around this thing
如果我在它们周围画一个盒子
and say this is AND of P and Q,
这就是(AND P Q)
then that box has exactly the same overall shape.
那么这个盒子也有同样的形状
It's something that takes in a stream from the database.
它也有一条连接数据库的流
Here it's going to get fanned out inside,
但是在内部会扇出开来
but from the outside you don't see that.
但是在外部你看不到
It takes an input stream and puts out an output stream.
它接收一个流 并输出一个流
So this is AND.
这就是AND
And then similarly, OR would look like this.
类似地 OR可能看起像这样
OR would-- although I didn't show you examples of OR.
虽然我没给你们演示过OR的用法
OR would say can I find all ways of matching P or Q.
OR会尝试找出P或Q所有匹配的事实
So I have P and Q. Each will have their shape.
P、Q两条查询都有各自的形状
And the way OR is implemented is
OR的实现则是
I'll take my database stream.
我把来自于数据库的流
I'll fan it out.
扇出开来
I'll put one into P and one into Q.
把它们分别送给P和Q
I'll take my initial query stream coming in and fan it out.
我把最初的查询流也给扇出开来
So I'll look at all the answers I might get from P
这样我不但能够得到P的所有结果
and all the answers I might get from Q,
也能得到Q的所有结果
and I'll put them through some sort of thing that appends them
把这些输出送入某种“附加器”中
or merges the result into one stream,
或者把它们“合并”到一条流中
and that's what will come out.
然后得到输出
And this whole thing from the outside is OR.
而从外部来看 这整个东西就是OR
And again, you see it has the same overall shape
同样的 当你们从外部观察它时
你会发现它具有相同的形状
What's NOT?
NOT又如何实现呢？
NOT works kind of the same way.
NOT的原理有些类似
If I have some query P,
如果我有一条查询P
If I have P, I take the primitive query for P.
这是一条基本查询P
Here, I'm going to implement NOT P.
现在我要实现(NOT P)
And NOT's just going to act as a filter.
NOT的作用像是一个过滤器
I'll take in the database
这里连接数据库
and my original stream of dictionaries coming in,
这里是输入的字典流
and what NOT P will do is
(NOT P)要做的就是
it will filter these guys.
对这些东西做过滤
And the way it will filter it,
过滤的方法则是
it will say when I get in a dictionary here,
如果我在这里获得了一本字典
I'll find all the matches,
那么我就去找所有的匹配
and if I find any, I'll throw it away.
然后丢弃找到的结果
And if I don't find any matches to something coming in here,
如果我没有在这里找到匹配
I'll just pass that through,
我就把它传递过去
so NOT is a pure filter.
NOT就是一个纯粹的过滤器
So AND is-- think of these sort of electoral resistors or something.
因此AND就类似于一个电阻
AND is series combination
AND是串行的组合
and OR is parallel combination.
OR是并行组合
And then NOT is not going to extend any dictionaries at all.
然而NOT并不会对字典做任何扩展
It's just going to filter it.
它只会做过滤
It's going to throw away the ones for which it finds a way to match.
它会丢弃那些能够匹配的结果
And lisp-value is sort of the same way.
LISP-VALUE的原理类似
The filter's a little more complicated.
它的过滤器会复杂点
It applies to predicate.
因为要应用到谓词上
The major point to notice here,
这里需要注意的关键点是
and it's a major point we've looked at before,
我们之前也强调过了
is this idea of closure.
就是关于“闭包性质”的思想
The things that we build as a means of combination
我们通过组合手段构建的东西
have the same overall structure
跟所使用的基本物件
as the primitive things that we're combining.
有同样的结构
So the AND of two things
所以从外面看
looked at from the outside has the same shape.
查询的AND与基本查询结构相同
And what that means is that
这就意味着
this box here could be an AND or an OR or a NOT or something
这里的盒子可以是AND、OR、NOT或者其它的
because it has the same shape to interface to the larger things.
因为它具有相同的形状来连接更大的东西
It's the same thing that allowed us to get
这种思想能够让我们获得
complexity in the Escher picture language
Escher绘图语言中的那种复杂度
or allows you to immediately build up these
让你能够仅仅使用序对
complicated structures just out of pairs.
构建出这些复杂结构
It's closure.
这就是“闭包性质”
And that's the thing that
这种性质
allowed me to do what by now you took for granted
能够让我完成你们现在觉得理所当然的事儿
I said, gee, there's a query which is AND of job and salary,
比如我可以查询(AND JOB SALARY)
and I said, oh, there's another one, which is AND of job, a NOT of something.
当然我也可以查询(AND JOB (NOT ...))等等
The fact that I can do that is
这种便利是由
a direct consequence of this closure principle.
这种“闭包原则”直接带给我们的
OK, let's break and then we'll go on.
好吧 提问时间
AUDIENCE: Where does the dictionary come from?
学生：字典是从哪里来的？
PROFESSOR: The dictionary comes initially from what you type in.
教授：字典最初来自于你的输入
So when you start this up,
因此当你最初进行查询时
the first thing it does is set up this whole structure.
它首先会建立起这整个结构
It puts in one empty dictionary.
它先输入一个空字典
And if all you have is one primitive query,
如果你只有一条基本查询的话
then what will come out is a bunch of dictionaries with things filled in.
那么它就会输出一系列具有内容的字典
The general situation that I have here
这里演示的一般性情况是
is when this is in the middle of some nest of combined things.
某个嵌套组合查询的中间过程
So by the time.
所以在那时
Let's look at the picture over here.
让我们来看看这里
This supervisor query gets in some dictionary.
这条SUPERVISOR查询得到了某本字典
Where did this one come from?
这本字典来自于哪里呢？
This dictionary came from the fact that
它来自于
I'm looking at the output of this primitive query.
这条基本查询的输出
So maybe to be very specific,
说得更具体一点
if I literally typed in just this query at the top level,
如果我最初在顶层只输入了这条查询
this AND,
这整条AND查询
what would actually happen is it would build this structure
它实际上会构建这种结构
and start up this whole thing with one empty dictionary.
并使用一本空字典来启动整个过程
And now this one would process, and a whole bunch of dictionaries
处理过程开始后 会产生一系列的字典
would come out with x, y's and d's in them.
其中就有X、Y以及D
Run it through this one.
向这边传递
So now that's the input to this one.
这就是这条查询的输入
This one would now put out some other stuff.
这条查询也会生成其它的东西
And if this itself were buried in some larger thing,
如果这整个查询是构建在一个更大的查询中的话
like an OR of something,
比如说一条OR查询
then that would go feed into the next one.
那么它将输出到下一个查询中
So you initially get only one empty dictionary when you start it,
因此最初开始处理时 只有一本空字典
but as you're in the middle of processing these compounds things,
但是在处理这些复合查询的过程中
that's where these cascades of dictionaries start getting generated.
会生成各种不同的字典
AUDIENCE: Dictionaries only come about as a result of using the queries?
学生：字典都是查询的结果吗？
Or do they stays, do they become--
它们会变成
do they stay someplace in space like the database does?
它们存储在数据库中吗？
Are these temporary items?
它们是临时数据吗？
PROFESSOR: They're created temporarily in the matcher.
教授：它们是在MATCH过程中临时创建的
Really, they're someplace in storage.
但它们实际存放在内存中
Initially, someone creates a thing called the empty dictionary
最初 某人创建了一本THE-EMPTY-DICT字典
that gets initially fed to this match procedure,
送入这个匹配过程
and then the match procedure builds some dictionaries,
MATCH过程据此构建新字典
and they get passed on and on.
并把它们传递下去
AUDIENCE: OK, so they'll go way after the match?
学生：因此匹配完成后它们就被丢弃了？
PROFESSOR: They'll go away when no one needs them again, yeah.
教授：实际上 当没人需要它们后（就被废料回收了）
AUDIENCE: It appears that the AND performs
学生：似乎AND查询对数据库
some redundant searches of the database.
进行了一些冗余操作
If the first clause matched,
如果第一条子句扫描过了
let's say, the third element and not on the first two elements,
比如说前两个元素没有匹配 而第三个元素匹配了
the second clause is going to look at those first two elements again,
然而第二条子句又会检查这两个元素
discarding them because they don't match.
然后又一次丢弃这些不匹配的元素
The match is already in the dictionary.
而字典中已经有匹配的项了
Would it makes sense to carry the data element
如果我们把数据库中的数据
from the database along with the dictionary?
跟字典同时传递 这样可行么？
PROFESSOR: Yeah, there're... Well, in general,
教授：实际上 通常来说
there are other ways to arrange this search,
我们能够以其它方式来安排这些搜索
and there's some analysis that you can do.
你也可以做一些分析
I think there's a problem in the book,
我记得书里面就有这样的习题
which talks about a different way that you can cascade AND
是考察通过安排AND子句的顺序
to eliminate various kinds of redundancies.
来消除不同类型的冗余
This one is meant to be--
而这里只是为了
was mainly meant to be very simple so you can see how they fit together.
用非常简单的情况来向你们展示它们是如何配合的
But you're quite right.
但是你说得非常对
There are redundancies here that you can get rid of.
这些冗余是可以避免的
That's another reason why this language is somewhat slow.
这也是这门语言缓慢的原因之一
There are a lot smarter things you can do.
你们可以让它变得更聪明
We're just trying to show you a very simple, in principle, implementation.
我只是为了向你们演示非常简单的、原理性的实现
AUDIENCE: Did you model this language on Prolog,
学生：您是根据Prolog来建模这门语言的
or did it just come out looking like Prolog?
还是说它只是偶然地像Prolog？
PROFESSOR: Well, Gerry insulted a whole bunch of people yesterday,
教授：Gerry教授昨天羞辱了一大堆人
so I might as well say that the MIT attitude towards Prolog is
我想说真实的情况是
is something that people did in about 1971
MIT的研究人员在1971年做了类似的事
and decided that it wasn't really the right thing and stopped.
但是发现这个方向并不正确 并停止了研究
So we modeled this on the sort of natural way that this thing was done
因此我们是根据查询处理的基本原理建模的
in about 1971,
大概在1971年左右
except at that point, we didn't do it with streams.
只是说 那时候我们还没有用流来实现
And then we... After we were using it for about six months,
然后我们 -- 但我们使用了它差不多六个月后
we discovered that it had all these problems,
发现它存在各种各样的问题
some of which I'll talk about later.
稍后我会解释
And we said,
然后我们就想
gee, Prolog must have fixed those,
Prolog一定解决了这些问题
and then we found out that it didn't.
但却发现它并没有
So this does about the same thing as Prolog.
从这种意义上来说 它确实跟Prolog一样
AUDIENCE: Does Prolog use streams?
学生：Prolog基于流么？
PROFESSOR: No. Prolog --
教授：不 Prolog基于的是
In how it behaves, it behaves a lot like Prolog.
就行为上来说 我们的语言很像Prolog
Prolog uses a backtracking strategy.
Prolog使用回溯策略
But the other thing that's really good about Prolog
但是Prolog有一个优点非常好
that makes it a usable thing
也使得它变得实用
is that there's a really very, very
你知道吗
there's a really very, very well-engineered compiler technology
它们精心设计了Prolog的编译器
that makes it run fast.
使得它能够高速运行
So although you saw the merge spitting out these answers very, very slowly,
因此 虽然我们这门语言非常缓慢地输出答案
a real Prolog will run very, very fast.
真正的Prolog程序却运行得非常快
Because even though it's sort of doing this,
这是因为 尽管搜索过程十分低效
the real work that went into Prolog is a very, very excellent compiler effort.
Prolog卓越的编译器也会高效地完成工作
Let's take a break.
休息一下吧
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
逻辑式程序设计 II
We've looked at the primitive queries
我们已经考察过了基本查询
and the ways that streams are used to implement the means of combination:
以及如何使用流来实现组合手段
AND and OR and NOT.
AND、OR以及NOT
Now, let go on to the means of abstraction.
现在 该讨论抽象手段了
Remember, the means of abstraction in this language are rules.
回想一下 我们这门语言的抽象手段是RULE
So z is a boss in division d
(BOSS ?Z ?D)描述的是
if there's some x who has a job in division d
如果某人在D部门工作
and z is the supervisor of x.
并且Z是X的上司
That's what it means for someone to be a boss.
这就是所谓的“BOSS”
So, and in effect,
并且 实际上
if you think about what we're doing with relation to this,
如果我们考察一下编写的规则与这边的关系
there's the query we wrote--
这是我们编写的查询
the job of x is in d and the supervisor of x is z--
这个是(JOB ?X ?D) 而这个是(SUPERVISOR ?X ?Z)
what we in effect want to do is take this whole mess
我们实际想要把这一大堆东西
and draw a box around it
用一个盒子封装起来
and say this whole thing inside the box
然后把这个盒子里的所有东西
is boss of z in division d.
认为是(BOSS ?Z ?D)
That's in effect what we want to do.
这是我们想要达到的效果
So, for instance,
因此 比如说
if we've done that,
我们这样做了过后
and we want to check whether or not it's true
我们想要检查
that Ben Bitdiddle is a boss in the computer division,
Ben Bitdiddle是否为计算机分部的BOSS
so if I want to say boss of Ben Bitdiddle in the computer division,
如果我想查询 (BOSS (BITDIDDLE BEN) COMPUTER)
imagine typing that in as query to the system,
想象一下把这条查询输入系统
in effect what we want to do
实际上发生的是
is set up a dictionary here,
在这里先构建一本字典
which has z to Ben Bitdiddle
其中 ?Z=BITDIDDLE
and d to computer.
?D=COMPUTER
Where did that dictionary come from?
这个字典又是来自于哪里呢？
Let's look at the slide for one second.
我们来看下幻灯片
That dictionary came from matching the query
这本字典是通过把
that said boss of Ben Bitdiddle and computer
查询(BOSS (BITDIDDLE BEN) COMPUTER)
onto the conclusion of the rule: boss of z and d.
与规则的结论(BOSS ?Z ?D)相匹配得到
So we match the query to the conclusion of the rule.
所以我们把规则的结论和查询匹配了起来
That gives us a dictionary,
这样我们就获得了一本字典
and that's the thing that we would now like to put into this whole big thing
现在我们就要把这本字典输入到这整个结构中
and process and see if anything comes out the other side.
进行处理 并观察是否有输出
If anything comes out, it'll be true.
如果输出了结果 那么查询就为真
That's the basic idea.
这是基本的思想
So in general,
因此 通常来说
the way we implement a rule
我们实现规则的方法就是
is we match the conclusion of the rule
用规则的结论去匹配
against something we might want to check it's true.
假设为真的查询
That match gives us a dictionary,
这个过程会产生一本字典
and with respect to that dictionary,
在有了相关字典后
we process the body of the rule.
我们来处理规则的体
Well, that's really all there is,
基本上就是这样了
except for two technical points.
但还有两个技术点
The first technical point is that
首先就是
I might have said something else.
我也可能有其它的问法
I might have said
比如说
who's the boss in the computer division?
查询计算机分部的BOSS
So I might say boss of who in computer division.
就可以查询 (BOSS ?WHO COMPUTER)
And if I did that,
这样做了以后
what I would really like to do in effect is not
我真正想要做的
is start up this dictionary
就是先建立一本字典
with a match that sort of says,
其中有一些约束
well, d is computer
比如 ?D=COMPUTER
and z is whatever who is.
而?Z等同于?WHO
And our matcher won't quite do that.
我们的匹配器不会那么做
That's not quite matching a pattern against data.
这不是模式和数据的匹配方式
It's matching two patterns
这是在匹配两个模式
sort of saying are they consistent or not
并判断它们是否一致
or what ways make them consistent.
又是什么使它们不一致
In other words, what we need is not quite a pattern matcher,
换句话说 我们需要的不是一个模式匹配器
but something a little bit more general
而是一种更一般性的东西
called a unifier.
就是“合一”算法
And a unifier is a slight generalization of a pattern matcher.
“合一”是更为一般化的模式匹配算法
What a unifier does is take two patterns
合一算法接收两条模式
and say what's the most general thing you can substitute
它考虑的是：可以找到哪些一般性的元素
for the variables in those two patterns
用来代换模式中的变量
to make them satisfy the pattern simultaneously?
使得它俩能够同时满足
Let me give you an example.
让我来举个例子
If I have the pattern two-element list, which is x and x,
我有一个含有两个元素的模式：(?X ?X)
so this is I have a two-element list
它描述的是一个二元表
where both elements are the same
不管元素具体是什么
and otherwise I don't care what they are,
但两个元素是相同的
and I unify that against the pattern
我把它与另一个模式进行“合一”
that says there's a two-element list,
后者描述的是一个二元表
and the first one is a and something and c
首元素一张由A、?Y、C构成的表
and the second one is a and b and z,
而第二个元素是由A、B、?Z构成的表
then what the unifier should tell me is,
那么 合一算法能够告诉我
oh yeah, in that dictionary,
在生成的字典中
x has to be a, b, c,
?X必须是(A B C)
and y has to be d and z has to be c.
?Y必须为B ?Z必须为C
Those are the restrictions I'd have to put on the values of x, y, and z
这些是我必须对X、Y以及Z施加的约束
to make these two unify,
以便让两个模式合一
or in other words, to make this match x
或者换句话来说 让它匹配这个?X
and make this match x.
让它匹配这个?X
The unifier should be able to deduce that.
合一算法需要能够推断出这些
But the unifier may-- there are more complicated things.
但是合一算法也会遇到复杂的情况
I might have said something a little bit more complicated.
我可能会询问一些复杂的查询
I might have said there's a list with two elements,
比如这是一个二元表
and they're both the same,
其中的元素都是相同的
and they should unify against something of this form.
它要与这个模式进行合一
And the unifier should be able to deduce from that.
合一算法也要能够从中推断出
Like that y would have to be b. y would have to be b.
?Y必须为B
Because these two are the same,
因为这两个是一样的
so y's got to be b.
因此?Y就是B
And v here would have to be a.
这里 ?V应该为A
And z and w can be anything,
只要?Z和?W取值相同
but they have to be the same thing.
它们就可以是任意值
And x would have to be b, followed by a, followed by whatever w
?X就应该是(B A ?W) 其中?W为任意值
or whatever z is, which is the same.
或者是?Z -- 因为?Z和?W是一致的
So you see, the unifier somehow has to deduce things to unify these patterns.
发现了么 合一算法需要从这些模式中推断出信息
So you might think there's some kind of magic deduction going on,
所以你们可能认为 这其中有某种魔法般的推理
but there's not.
但其实并不是
A unifier is basically a very simple modification of a pattern matcher.
合一算法基本上只是对模式匹配的小小修改
And if you look in the book, you'll see something like
如果你们翻阅教材 就会发现
like three or four lines of code added to the pattern matcher you just saw
在模式匹配算法中加入了三到四行代码
to handle the symmetric case.
来处理对称的情况
Remember, the pattern matcher has a place where it says
还记得吗 模式匹配中有一处代码判断
is this variable matching a constant.
这个变量匹配一个常量吗？
And if so, it checks in the dictionary.
如果是的话 就在字典中进行检查
There's only one other clause in the unifier,
在合一算法中只有另一条子句
which says is this variable matching a variable,
它判断两个变量是否相匹配
in which case you go look in the dictionary
这种情况下你去查询字典
and see if that's consistent with what's in the dictionary.
看它们在字典的约束下是否一致
So all the, quote, deduction that's in this language,
因此 这门语言中的所有“推断”
if you sort of look at it, sort of sits in the rule applications,
你会发现它蕴含在规则应用中
which, if you look at that, sits in the unifier,
更进一步地考察 你会发现在合一算法中
which, if you look at that under a microscope,
如果更进一步地用“显微镜”观察
sits essentially in the pattern matcher.
基本上就在模式匹配算法中
There's no magic at all going on in there.
这其中并没有什么魔法
And the, quote, deduction that you see
而你们所见到的“推断”
is just the fact that there's this recursion,
只是因为其中的递归
which is unwinding the matches bit by bit.
它一点一点地回绕MATCH过程
So it looks like this thing is being very clever,
它让这个过程看起来很聪明
but in fact, it's not being very clever at all.
但它实际上并不是那么聪明
There are cases where a unifier might have to be clever.
当然 合一算法需要聪明地识别出一些情况
Let me show you one more.
我来举个例子吧
Suppose I want to unify a list of two elements,
假设我想要用一个二元表进行合一
x and x,
(?X ?X)
with a thing that says it's y followed by a dot y.
另一个模式则是 (?Y (a . ?Y))
Now, if you think of what that would have to mean,
现在 如果你想一想它所表达的意思
it would have to mean that x had better be the same as y,
它表示了?X应该跟?Y一致
but also
同时呢
x had better be the same as a list whose first element is a and whose rest is y.
?X又应该跟(A . ?Y)相同
And if you think about what that would have to mean,
如果你仔细思考它成立的条件
it would have to mean that y is the infinite list of a's.
你会发现 ?Y必须是一个由A构成的无穷表
In some sense,
从某种角度来说
in order to do that unification,
为了完成这样的合一
I have to solve the fixed-point equation
我需要求解一个不动点方程
cons of a to y is equal to y.
(CONS 'A Y)=Y
And in general, I wrote a very simple one.
通常来说 --- 我这个例子很简单
Really doing unification
但实际进行合一时
might have to solve an arbitrary fixed-point equation:
我们可能要求解一个任意的不动点方程
f of y equals y.
(F Y)=Y
And basically, you can't do that
你基本上不能保证
and make the thing finite all the time.
在有穷时间内找到解
So how does the logic language handle that?
我们的逻辑语言又该如何处理这类情况呢？
The answer is it doesn't.
答案就是：“不处理”
It just punts.
它会撒手不干
And there's a little check in the unifier,
合一算法中有一处小检查
which says, oh, is this one of the hard cases
用来判断是否为困难的情况
which when I go to match things would involve solving a fixed-point equation?
也就是 匹配这些东西需要求解不动点方程
And in this case, I will throw up my hands.
遇到这类情况 我就撒手不干
And if that check were not in there,
如果不进行这样的检查
what would happen?
会发生什么情况？
In most cases is
大多数情况就是
that the unifier would just go into an infinite loop.
合一算法会陷入无穷循环
And other logic programming languages work like that.
其它的逻辑语言有类似的工作原理
So there's really no magic.
因此这其中没有什么魔法
The easy case is done in a matcher.
简单的情况由匹配器完成
The hard case is not done at all.
困难的情况根本不去处理
And that's about the state of this technology.
这就是这种技术的现状
OK, Let me just say again formally
现在 我来形式化地描述一下
how rules work now that I talked about unifiers.
规则系统的运行原理 -- 也就是合一算法
So the official definition
因此 正式的定义就是
is that to apply a rule,
应用一条规则
we-- well, let's start using some words we've used before.
我们需要使用一些之前的术语
Let's talk about sticking dictionaries into
我们把向查询的盒子中
these big boxes of query things
塞入字典称作是
as evaluating these large queries
相对一个环境或者框架
relative to an environment or a frame.
对这些大型查询求值
So when you think of that dictionary,
因此 当我们谈及“字典”的时候
what's the dictionary after all?
“字典”究竟是什么？
It's a bunch of meanings for symbols.
它是符号的一系列语义
That's what we've been calling frames or environments.
我们把它叫做“框架”或者“环境”
What does it mean to do some processing relevant to an environment?
根据环境进行操作 又是什么？
That's what we've been calling evaluation.
我们把这个叫做“求值”
So we can say the way that you apply a rule
因此我们就说 应用一条规则的方法是
is to evaluate the rule body relative to an environment
先通过将给定的查询与规则的结论合一 得到环境
that's formed by unifying the rule conclusion with the given query.
再在该环境中求值相应规则的体
And the thing I want you to notice
我想要让你们注意的是
is the complete formal similarity
这非常像是
to the net of circular evaluator or the substitution model.
元循环求值器以及代换模型
To apply a procedure,
规则的应用就是
we evaluate the procedure body relative to an environment
在一个环境中求值规则的体
that's formed by blinding the procedure parameters to the arguments.
环境是通过将实际参数与形式参数绑定起来得到的
There's a complete formal similarity there
规则、规则的应用、过程的应用
between the rules, rule application, and procedure application
它们在形式上完全相似
even though these things are very, very different.
尽管它们又非常不同
And again, you have the EVAL APPLY loop.
再一次地出现了EVAL-APPLY循环
EVAL and APPLY.
EVAL-APPLY
So in general, I might be processing some combined expression
因此通常来说 我们可能会处理一些复合表达式
that will turn into a rule application,
它们会变成规则的应用
which will generate some dictionaries or frames or environments--
进一步又会产生字典、框架或者环境
whatever you want to call them-- from match,
不管你要怎么叫它
which will then be the input to some big compound thing like this.
它们随后又会作为某个大的复合对象的输入
This has pieces of it and may have other rule applications.
这有它的一部分 并可能有其它规则的应用
And you have essentially the same cycle
这基本上就是相同的循环
even though there's nothing here at all that looks like procedures.
尽管这里没有什么东西看起来像过程
It really has to do with the fact you've built a language
这是因为我们创建的语言
whose means of combination and abstraction unwind in certain ways.
它们的组合手段和抽象手段以某种方式展开
And then in general,
通常来说
what happens at the very top level,
最顶层所发生的是
you might have rules in your database also,
数据库中也有一些规则
so things in this database might be rules.
数据库中的数据也可能是规则
There are ways to check that things are true.
它们用来检查对象是否为真
So it might come in here and have to do a rule check.
所以这里可能会有规则检查
And then there's some control structure
然后就会有一些控制结构
which says, well, you look at some rules, and you look at some data elements,
用来判断你访问的是规则
and you look at some rules and data elements,
还是数据元素
and these fan out and out and out.
然后不断地把它们扇出来开
So it becomes essentially impossible
所以基本上不可能说清楚
to say what order it's looking at these things in,
是用什么样的顺序来查询这些东西的
whether it's breadth first or depth first or anything.
是广度优先还是深度优先
And it's even more impossible
另外一个原因是
because the actual order is somehow buried in the delays of the streams.
我们通过惰性流隐藏了实际执行顺序
So what's very hard to tell from this is the order in which it's scanned.
因此很难说清楚它的扫描顺序
But what's true is,
但真实的是
because you're looking at the stream view,
由于你是在流视图观察它的
is that all of them eventually get looked at.
而它们最终都要被扫描到
Let me just mention one tiny technical problem.
这里还有一个小小的技术问题
Um Suppose I tried over here.
假设我在这里输入
Suppose I tried saying boss of y is computer,
假设我输入(BOSS ?Y COMPUTER)
then a funny thing would happen.
然后就会发生一件有意思的事儿
As I stuck a dictionary with y in here,
这里的字典就有一项?Y
I might get-- this y is not the same as that y,
而这两个?Y是不相同的
which was the other piece of somebody's job description.
后者是其它人的工作描述
So if I really only did literally what I said,
因此 按照输入“照本宣科”地执行的话
we'd get some variable conflict problems.
我们就会遇到变量冲突的问题
So I lied to you a little bit.
所以我骗了你们一下
Notice that problem is exactly a problem we've run into before.
注意 我们之前也遇到过同样的问题
It is precisely
具体来说就是
the need for local variables in a language.
一门语言需要局部变量
When I square, when I have the sum of squares,
当我计算SQUARE和SUM-SQUARES的时候
that x had better not be that x.
这两个X应该是不同的
That's exactly the same as
同样的道理
as this y had better not be that y.
这两个?Y应该也不相同
And we know how to solve that.
我们知道该如何解决
We built -- That was this whole environment model,
就是引入环境模型
and we built chains of frames and all sorts of things like that.
我们构建类似于“框架链”一类的东西
There's a much more brutal way to solve it.
还有更加“粗暴”的解决方法
In the query language, we didn't even do that.
在查询语言中 我们根本不这么做
We did something completely brutal.
我们的解决方法非常粗暴
We said every time you apply a rule,
我们规定 每次你在应用一条规则的时候
rename consistently all the variables in the rule
用一个不会引起冲突的唯一名字
to some new unique names that won't conflict with anything.
统一地为规则中的所有变量更名
If you looked at the -- That's conceptually simpler,
这个从概念上来说更简单
but really brutal and not particularly efficient.
但既粗暴 又不是很有效
But notice,
但是请注意
we could have gotten rid of all of our environment structures
如果我们对Lisp中定义的过程也这么处理
if we defined for procedures in Lisp the same thing.
那么就不需要环境模型了
If every time we applied a procedure and did the substitution model
如果我们每次在应用一个过程的时候
we renamed all the variables in the procedure,
我们为过程中的所有变量更名
then we never would have had to worry about local variables
那么我们就不需要担心局部变量了
because they would never arise.
因为它们不会出现
OK, well, that would be inefficient,
但这种做法比较低效
and it's inefficient here in the query language, too,
在我们的查询语言中同样也比较低效
but we did it to keep it simple.
但我们还是这样做了 并让它保持简单
Let's break for questions.
有问题吗？
AUDIENCE: When you started this section,
学生：您这一小节开始的时候
you emphasized how powerful our APPLY EVAL model was
就强调APPLY-EVAL模型是多么的强大
that we could use it for any language.
以至于任何语言都适用
And then you say we're going to have this language which is so different.
但你又说这门语言将会非常不同
It turns out that this language,
但最后却发现这门语言
as you just pointed out, is very much the same.
就像你指出的那样--也是同样的
I'm wondering if you're arguing that all languages end up
我在想 您是否是在论证
coming down to this you can apply a rule or apply a procedure
所有的语言都可以转化成 规则或过程的应用
or some kind of apply?
或者类似的
PROFESSOR: I would say that pretty much any language
教授：可以说 几乎所有语言
where you really are building up
我们通过组合手段构建对象
these means of combination and giving them simpler names
用简单的名字给它们命名
and you're saying anything of the sort, like
你可以把任何类似的 比如
here's a general kind of expression,
有一种一般性的表达式
like how to square something,
比如说如何计算某数的平方
almost anything that you would call a procedure.
几乎所有的东西都可以称为“过程”
If that's got to have parts,
如果语言中有这么一部分的话
you have to unwind those parts.
那么你就需要能够展开它们
You have to have some kind of organization which says
你需要有某种组织 使得
when I look at the abstract variables or tags
当你查看这些抽象变量 或者说标签的时候
or whatever you want to call them that might stand for particular things,
它们可能代表着某些特定的东西
you have to keep track of that,
你必须一直跟踪它们
and that's going to be something like an environment.
这就会形成类似于环境的结构
And then if you say
让后当你要
this part can have parts which I have to unwind,
展开复合对象其中的一个部分的时候
you've got to have something like this cycle.
你就需要EVAL-APPLY循环了
And lots and lots of languages have that character
有很多很多的语言有这样的特点
as long ... when they sort of get put together in this way.
它们也是按这种方式组织的
This language again really is different
而这门语言特殊之处在于
because there's nothing like procedures on the outside.
从外界看 并没有“过程”
When you go below the surface and you see the implementation,
而当你剖开表层 深入到实现中去
of course, it starts looking the same.
当然 你会发现本质是一样的
But from the outside, it's a very different world view.
但是从外界来看 这是一种非常不同的世界观
You're not computing functions of inputs.
你没有计算输入的函数
AUDIENCE: You mentioned earlier that
学生：您之前提到过
when you build all of these rules in pattern matcher
当用模式匹配来实现这些规则时
and with the delayed action of streams,
由于使用了流实现延迟求值
you really have no way to know
所以没有办法知道
in what order things are evaluated.
对象的求值顺序
PROFESSOR: Right.
教授：是这样的
AUDIENCE: And that would indicate then that
学生：但这就表明
you should only express declarative knowledge that's true for all-time,
我们只能表达总是为真的陈述性知识
no-time sequence built into it.
语言并不支持时间序列
Otherwise, these things get all--
否则的话 后果就会--
PROFESSOR: Yes. Yes.
教授：是的 非常正确
The question is
问题在于
this really is set up for doing declarative knowledge,
这个本来就是用来处理陈述性知识的
and as I presented it-- no
而就我目前所演示的来说 不支持
and I'll show you some of the ugly warts under this after the break.
休息之后我会向你们揭露这其中的丑陋之处
As I presented it, it's just doing logic.
就如我目前所展示的 它只是进行逻辑运算
And in principle, if it were logic,
原理上来说 如果我们做的是逻辑运算
it wouldn't matter what order it's getting done.
用什么顺序完成并不会造成影响
And it's quite true
但是呢
when you start doing things where you have side effects
当你在进行一些具有副作用的操作的时候
like adding things to the database
比如向数据库中添加项
and taking things out, and we'll see some others,
从中取出项 等等操作
you loose that kind of control.
你就丧失了这类控制
So, for example, contrasting with Prolog.
因此 这就与Prolog完全不同
Say Prolog has various features
Prolog有各种功能
where you really exploit the order of evaluation.
能够让你利用求值的顺序
And people write Prolog programs that way.
人们也这么来写Prolog
That turns out to be very complicated in Prolog,
结果发现这样变得非常困难
although if you're an expert Prolog programmer, you can do it.
但如果你是Prolog程序专家 你就可以这么做
However, here I don't think you can do it at all.
但是我认为你们现在并不可以
It's very complicated
它相当复杂
because you really are giving up control over
因为你们放弃了对事先安排的
any prearranged order of trying things.
求值顺序的控制权
AUDIENCE: Now, that would indicate then that you have a functional mapping.
学生：这就表明 当你有一个函数式映射时
And when you started out this lecture,
而你最初在讲这门课的时候
you said that
你说过
we express the declarative knowledge which is a relation,
我们在表述作为关系的陈述性知识
and we don't talk about the inputs and the outputs.
因为我们讨论的不是输入和输出
PROFESSOR: Well, there's a pun on functional, right?
教授：这是关于“函数式”的双关语
There's functional in the sense of no side effects
一种是没有副作用
and not depending on what order is going on.
因此并不依赖于求值的顺序
And then there's functional in the sense of mathematical function,
还有就是数学意义上的“函数”
which means input and output.
有关于输入和输出
And it's just that pun that you're making, I think.
我想这就是你想表达的双关
AUDIENCE: I'm a little unclear on what you're doing with
学生：我对其中两条语句不太明白
two statements, the two boss statements.
也就是那两条有关BOSS的语句
Is the first one building up the database
是不是 第一条查询构建了一个数据库
and the second one a query or--
然后第二条查询--
PROFESSOR: OK, I'm sorry.
教授：抱歉
What I meant here, if I type something like this in as a query--
这里的意思是 如果我输入这样的查询
I should have given an example way at the very beginning.
我应该最初就给你们举这个例子
If I type in job, Ben Bitdiddle, computer wizard,
如果我输入(JOB (BITDIDDLE BEN) (COMPUTER WIZARD))
what the processing will do is if it finds a match,
系统会找到一处事实
it'll find a match to that exact thing,
来完全匹配这条查询
and it'll type out a job, Ben Bitdiddle, computer wizard.
然后输出(JOB (BITDIDDLE BEN) (COMPUTER WIZARD))
If it doesn't find a match,
如果没找到这样的匹配
it won't find anything.
它就什么也不输出
So what I should have said is the way
我应该这么来表述
you use the query language to check whether something is true,
这门语言是用来查询某个表述是否为真
that's one of the things you want to do in logic programming,
这是逻辑式编程的目的之一
is you type in your query and either that comes out or it doesn't.
输入一条查询 要么得到结果 要么没有
So what I was trying to illustrate here,
因此 我这里想要演示的是
I wanted to start with a very simple example
我想要在介绍合一算法前
before talking about unifiers.
举一个简单的例子
So what I should have said,
所以 我应该说
if I just wanted to check whether this is true,
如果我想要检查 这个是否为真
I could type that in and see if anything came out
我就可以将它输入 并看有没有任何输出
AUDIENCE: And then the second one--
学生：然后第二条查询
PROFESSOR: The second one would be a real query.
教授：第二条就是真正意义上的“查询”
AUDIENCE: A real query, yeah.
学生：好的 真正的查询
PROFESSOR: What would come out, see, it would go in here say with WHO,
教授：在这里它就会输出与?WHO相关的信息
and in would go frame that says z
就会有一个框架 存储着
z is bound to who and d is bound to computer.
?Z=?WHO ?D=COMPUTER
And this will pass through,
这个会传递下去
and then by the time it got out of here,
传递到这里的时候
who would pick up a binding.
?WHO就会被绑定起来
AUDIENCE: On the unifying thing there,
学生：在合一那里
I still am not sure what happens with who and z.
我还是不太清楚?WHO和?Z之间发生了什么
OK being unifying-- the rule here says--
要进行合一的话 这里的规则说
OK, so you say that you can't make question mark equal to question mark who.
你说过 两个模式变量之间不能互相绑定
PROFESSOR: Right. That's what the matcher can't do.
教授：模式匹配器确实不能这样
But unifier, what this will mean to a unifier
但对合一算法来说
is that there's an environment with three variables.
就是一个有存储三个变量的环境
d here is computer.
其中?D=COMPUTER
z is whatever who is.
?Z=?WHO
So if later on in the matcher routine
所以在稍后的匹配过程中
it said, for example, who has to be 3,
如果?WHO=3
then when I looked up in the dictionary,
那么当我再查找字典的时候
it will say, oh, z is 3 because it's the same as who.
它会告诉我 因为?Z=?WHO 所以?Z=3
And that's in some sense the only thing you need to do
从某种意义上来说 你就只需要修改这一点
to extend the unifier to a matcher.
就可以把合一算法变成模式匹配器
AUDIENCE: OK, because it looked like when you were telling how to unify,
学生：但是看起来你好像告诉了它 如何进行合一
it looked like you would put the things together in such a way
就像你已经解好了方程 准备好了值
that you'd actually solve and have a value for both of them.
并把它们安排成这样
And what it looks like now
现在看起来就像是
is that you're actually pass a dictionary
你传递了一本字典
with two variables and the variables are linked.
其中的两个变量是关联起来的
PROFESSOR: Right. It only looks like you're solving for both of them
教授：实际上 我们在同时求解它们
because you're sort of looking at the whole solution at once.
这是因为我们想要一下得到整个答案
If you sort of watch the thing getting built up recursively,
如果你观察它们是如何被递归地构建的
it's merely this.
基本上就是这样了
AUDIENCE: OK, so you do pass off that dictionary with two variables?
学生：也就是确实要传递含有两个变量的字典？
PROFESSOR: That's right.
教授：是的
AUDIENCE: And link?
学生：然后把它们关联起来？
PROFESSOR: Right. It just looks like an ordinary dictionary.
教授：就像通常的字典那样
AUDIENCE: When you're talking about the unifier,
学生：你在讨论合一算法的时候
is it that there are some cases or some points
你说过在某些情况下
that you are not able to unify them?
合一不能够完成
PROFESSOR: Right.
教授：是的
AUDIENCE: Can you just by building the rules or
学生：那么 是否可以通过编写规则
writing the forms know in advance if you are going to be able to solve
或者 写入那些事先知道可解的形式
to get the unification or not?
来使得合一算法能够完成
Can you add some properties either to the rules itself
是否可以在规则中添加一些属性
or to the form that you're writing
或者向输入的形式中添加属性
so that you avoid the problem of not finding unification?
来避免无法进行合一的窘境
Well I mean, you can agree,
PROFESSOR: 我想 你也同意
I think, to write in a fairly restricted way where you won't run into it.
用非常受限的方式来编写查询
See, because what you're getting--
看 你遇到的是
see, the place where you get into problems is when you--
仔细看 你遇到问题是在
well, again, you're trying to match things like that
用像这样的东西去匹配
against things where these have structure,
具有这样结构的模式时
where a, y, b, y something.
比如((A ?Y B) ?Y)
So this is the kind of place where you're going to get into trouble.
这是你可能遇到问题的一个地方
AUDIENCE: So you can do that syntactically?
学生：所以你可以在语法层次上处理它么？
PROFESSOR: So you can kind of watch your rules
教授：你可以在写查询时
in the kinds of things that your writing.
注意你的规则
AUDIENCE: So that's the problem that the builder
学生：这个问题应该由
of the database has to be concerned?
数据库的构建者考虑么？
PROFESSOR: That's a problem.
教授：这个问题
It's a problem either-- not quite the builder of the database,
不完全是数据库的构建者
the person who is expressing the rules,
或者是表述规则的人
or the builder of the database.
所需要考虑的
What the unifier actually does is you can check at the next level down
当你们仔细审查合一算法的代码时
when you actually get to the unifier
你们会发现
and you'll see in the code where it looks up in the dictionary.
它实际上在查询一个字典
If it sort of says what does y have to be?
它会问 ?Y的取值应该是什么？
Oh, does y have to be something that contains a y as its expression?
?Y应该是一个含有自包含的表达式么？
At that point, the unifier and say,
这时候 合一算法就会说
oh my God, I'm trying to solve a fixed-point equation.
哦 我正在求解一个不动点方程
I'll give it up here.
我还是放弃吧
AUDIENCE: You make the distinction between the rules in the database.
学生：你区分过数据库中的规则
Are the rules added to the database?
这些规则是加入数据库的么？
PROFESSOR: Yes.
教授：是的
Yes, I should have said that.
我应该这么来说
One way to think about rules
你们可以把规则看作
is that they're just other things in the database.
数据库中的其它东西
So if you want to check the things that have to be checked in the database,
如果你想要检查数据库中需要检查的东西
they're kind of virtual facts that are in the database.
它们就是存在于数据库中的虚拟事实
AUDIENCE: But in that explanation, you made the differentiation
学生：但是在这个解释中
between database and the rules itself.
你就已经区分了数据库和规则本身
PROFESSOR: Yeah, I probably should not have done that.
教授：是的 我应该不这么来说
The only reason to do that is in terms of the implementation.
这样做的唯一理由就是实现
When you look at the implementation,
当你们查看具体实现时
there's a part which says check either primitive
会发现其中有部分用来检查数据库中的
assertions in the database or check rules.
基本断言或者规则
And then the real reason, the real reason why
这其中的真正原因就是
you can't tell what order things are going to come out in
你不知道查询结果是以什么顺序输出的
is that the rules database and the data database
而规则数据库和数据数据库
sort of get merged in a kind of delayed evaluation way.
是通过某种延迟求值的方式合并的
And so that's what makes the order very complicated.
这就使得顺序变得非常复杂
OK, let's break.
那好 我们休息一下
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
[音乐]
《计算机程序的构造和解释》
讲师：哈罗德·艾伯森教授 及 格兰德·杰·萨斯曼教授
逻辑式程序设计 II
We've just seen how the logic language works
我们已经学习了逻辑式语言与
and how rules work.
规则系统的运行原理
Now, let's turn to a more profound question.
现在 让我们来探讨一个更加深刻的问题
What do these things mean?
来看下它们意味着什么
That brings us to the subtlest, most devious part
这把我们带入到整个查询语言中
of this whole query language business,
最微妙的部分
and that is that it's not quite what it seems to be.
也就是它看起来与想象中不同的地方
AND and OR and NOT
AND、OR以及NOT
and the logical implication of rules
以及规则的逻辑蕴含
are not really the AND and OR and NOT and logical implication of logic.
并不是逻辑学中的与、或、非以及蕴含
Let me give you an example of that.
让我来举一个实例
Certainly, if we have two things in logic,
当然 如果我们有两个逻辑命题
it ought to be the case that AND of P and Q
那么(AND P Q)就应该
is the same as AND of Q and P
等同于(AND Q P)
and that OR of P and Q
而(OR P Q)就应该
is the same as OR of Q and P.
等同于(OR Q P)
But let's look here.
但我们来看看这里
Here's an example.
这里是一个例子
Let's talk about somebody outranking somebody else
来看看 在我们的数据库中
in this our little database organization.
如何表示某人的级别高于他人
We'll say s is outranked by b
我们定义(OUTRANKED-BY ?S ?B)为
if or if either the supervisor of s is b
或者S是B的上司
or there's some middle manager here,
或者这其中有某个中间经理M
that supervisor of s is m, and m is outranked by b.
其中S是M的上司 M的级别又比B高
So there's one way to define rule outranked by.
这是定义OUTRANKED-BY的一种方式
Or we can write exactly the same thing,
或者我们可以原封不动地写过来
except at the bottom here,
除了在最底部的这里
we reversed the order of these two clauses.
我们颠倒一下这两个子句的顺序
And certainly if this were logic,
当然 如果它们都是逻辑表达式的话
those ought to mean the same thing.
它们应该表示的是相同的东西
However,
然而
in our particular implementation,
在我们这个特定的实现中
if you say something like who's outranked by Ben Bitdiddle,
如果你查询(OUTRANDKED-BY ?WHO (BITDIIDLE BEN))
what you'll find is that this rule
你会发现 这条规则
will work perfectly well and generate answers,
会完美地生成答案
whereas this rule will go into an infinite loop.
然而 这条规则会陷入无穷循环
And the reason for that is that
其中的原因就是
this will come in and say, oh, who's outranked by Ben Bitdiddle?
这条规则会问谁比BEN BITDIDDLE级别高？
Find an s, find an s
它试图寻找一个S
which is outranked by b, where b is Ben Bitdiddle,
使得S比B的级别更高 其中B是BEN BITDIDDLE
which is going to happen in it a subproblem.
这会在一个子问题中重复出现
Oh gee, find an m
找到一个M
such as m is outranked by Ben Bitdiddle
使得M的级别高于BEN BITDIDDLE
with no restrictions on m.
而对M没有限制
So this will say in order to solve this problem,
这就相当于为了解决这个问题
I solve exactly the same problem.
我就还需要求解同样的问题
And then after I've solved that, I'll check for a supervisory relationship.
在把它解出来后 我才检查SUPERVISOR关系
Whereas this one won't get into that,
然而这条规则没有这样的问题
because before it tries to find this outranked by,
因为在它尝试找出这条OUTRANKED-BY规则之前
it'll already have had a restriction on m here.
在这里已经对M施加过约束了
So these two things which ought to mean the same,
随意 这两条规则理论上是相同的
in fact, one goes into an infinite loop.
但实际上 其中一条会陷入无穷循环
One goes, one does not.
而另一条不会
That's a very extreme case
通过这个非常极端的例子
of a general thing that you'll find in logic programming that
你会发现在逻辑式程序设计中
if you start changing the order of the things in the ANDs or ORs,
如果你改变了AND或OR所连接子句的顺序
you'll find tremendous differences in efficiency.
你会发现效率上的巨大差异
And we just saw
我们刚刚就看到了
an infinitely big difference in efficiency and an infinite loop.
在无穷循环方面的巨大差异
And there are similar things having to do order
同样的 这也跟输入规则
in which you enter rules.
的顺序有关
The order in which it happens to look at rules in the database
向数据库查询规则的顺序
may vastly change the efficiency with which it gets out answers or,
会极大程度上影响效率：比如得到答案
in fact, send it into an infinite loop for some orderings.
或者在某些顺序下陷入无穷循环
And this whole thing has to do
这些都跟
the fact that you're checking these rules in some order.
你检查这些规则的顺序有关
And some rules may lead to really long paths of implication.
有些规则的蕴含路径会相当的长
Others might, others might not.
而另外一些不会
And you don't know a priori
但你事先并不知道
which ones are good and which ones are bad.
哪一个长 哪一个短
And there's a whole bunch of research having to do with that,
有很多研究都与此有关
mostly having to do with thinking about
其中大多数都是想通过
making parallel implementations of logic programming languages.
用并行的方法来实现逻辑式程序设计语言
And in some sense, what you'd like to do is check all rules in parallel
某种意义上来说 就是并行地检查所有规则
and whichever ones get answers, you bubble them up. And
一旦有一条搜索得到答案 就返回结果
if some go down infinite deductive chain,
如果某条路径陷入了无穷的推导
well, you just-- you know, memory is cheap and processors are cheap,
那么 你只需知道 内存和处理器都非常廉价
you just let them buzz for as for as long as you want.
让它们根据你的需要一直搜寻就好了
There's a deeper problem, though,
尽管如此 与真正的逻辑相比
in comparing this logic language to real logic.
这门逻辑式语言还有一个更深刻的问题
The example I just showed you, it
我给你们演示的例子
went into an infinite loop maybe,
只是会陷入无穷循环
but at least it didn't give the wrong answer.
但至少不会给你错误的答案
There's an actual deeper problem when we start comparing,
当我们开始严肃地把这门逻辑式语言
you know, seriously comparing
与真正的经典逻辑作比较时
this logic language with real classical logic.
就会发现其中最深层次的问题
So let's sort of review real classical logic.
让我们来看看真正的经典逻辑
All humans are mortal.
所有的人类都是凡人
That's pretty classical logic.
相当经典的逻辑命题
Then maybe we'll continue in the very best classical tradition.
然后我们就依照最经典的传统
We'll say all-- let's make it really classical.
我们按照最传统的方式来做
All Greeks are human,
所有的希腊人都是人类
which has the syllogism that Socrates is a Greek.
苏格拉底是希腊人
And then what do you write here?
然后我们又该写什么呢？
I think three dots, classical logic.
经典逻辑中有一个三点符号
Therefore, then the syllogism,
因此 我们得到了一个三段论
Socrates is mortal.
苏格拉底是凡人
So there's some real honest classical logic.
这些都是真正的经典逻辑
Let's compare that with our classical logic database.
把它跟我们经典逻辑数据库比较一下
So here's a classical logic database.
这是一个经典逻辑数据库
Socrates is a Greek.
(GREEK SOCRATES)
Plato is a Greek.
(GREEK PLATO)
Zeus is a Greek,
(GREEK ZEUS)
and Zeus is a god.
(GOD ZEUS)
And all humans are mortal.
所有的人类都是凡人
To show that something is mortal,
为了证明某人是平凡的
it's enough to show that it's human.
只需要证明他是人类
All humans are fallible.
所有的人类都是不可靠的
And all Greeks are humans is not quite right.
并且说所有的希腊人都是人类 并不正确
This says that all Greeks who are not gods are human.
这条规则说 所有不是神的希腊人都是人类
So to show something's human,
因此为了证明某人是人类
it's enough to show it's a Greek and not a god.
只需要说明他是一个希腊人 并且不是神
And the address of any Greek god is Mount Olympus.
任何一个希腊神的住址是奥林匹斯山
So there's a little classical logic database.
这就是一个小型经典逻辑数据库
And indeed, that would work fairly well.
确实 它运行得相当好
If we type that in and say
如果我们向其询问
is Socrates mortal or Socrates fallible or mortal?
苏格拉底是凡人么 不可靠么？
It'll say yes.
它会输出：是
Is Plato mortal and fallible.
柏拉图是凡人并且不可靠么？
It'll say yes.
它会回答：是
If we say is Zeus mortal?
如果我们问宙斯是凡人么
It won't find anything.
它什么都不会找到
And it'll work perfectly well.
运行得非常完美
However, suppose we want to extend this.
然而 如果我们想要把它扩展一下
Let's define what it means for someone to be a perfect being.
让我们来定义一下什么是“完美生命体”
Let's say rule: a perfect being.
我们把规则PERFECT定义为
And I think this is right.
我想这样来定义是正确的
If you're up on your medieval scholastic philosophy,
如果你熟悉中世纪经院哲学
I believe that perfect beings are ones
我想所谓“完美生命体”一定
who were neither mortal nor fallible.
既不是凡人 又不会不可靠
AND NOT mortal x, NOT fallible x.
(AND (NOT (MORTAL ?X)) (NOT (FALLIBLE ?X)))
So we'll define this system
这样 我们就定义了一个规则
to teach it what a perfect being is.
来告诉系统 什么是“完美生命体”
And now what we're going to do is
现在 我们就要
ask for the address of all the perfect beings.
询问所有“完美生命体”的地址
AND the address of x is y and x is perfect.
(AND (ADDRESS ?X ?Y) (PERFECT ?X))
And so what we're generating here is
在这里 我们生成了
the world's most exclusive mailing list.
世界上最独有的邮件列表
For the address of all the perfect beings,
为了查询所有完美生命体的地址
we might have typed this in.
我们会输入像这样的查询
Or we might type in this.
或者像这样输入
We'll say AND perfect of x and the address of x is y.
(AND (PERFECT ?X) (ADDRESS ?X ?Y))
Well, suppose we type all that in and we try this query.
假设我们把它输入进去 并尝试查询
This query is going to give us an answer.
这条查询会给我们答案
This query will say, yeah, Mount Olympus.
这条查询会输出：奥林匹斯山
This query, in fact, is going to give us nothing.
而这条查询 什么也不会输出
It will say no addresses of perfect beings.
它找不到完美生命体的地址
Now, why is that?
为什么会这样？
Why is there a difference?
这又为什么不同？
This is not an infinite loop question.
这个问题跟无穷循环没什么关系
This is a different answer question.
这个的问题是答案不相同
The reason is
原因就是
that if you remember the implementation of NOT,
如果你们还记得NOT的实现的话
NOT acted as a filter.
NOT是作为一个过滤器
NOT said I'm going to take some possible dictionaries,
NOT会接收一本字典
some possible frames, some possible answers,
里面有可行解构成的框架
and filter out the ones
然后过滤出那些
that happened to satisfy some condition,
满足某个条件的解
and that's how I implement NOT.
这就是我如何实现NOT的
If you think about what's going on here,
如果你们仔细想想其中的原理
I'll build this query box where the address piece
我创建了一个查询盒子
the output of an address piece gets fed into a perfect piece.
ADDRESS盒子的输出作为了PERFECT的输入
What will happen is
这就使得
the address piece will set up some things of
ADDRESS盒子会创建出
everyone whose address I know.
我知道地址的人
Those will get filtered by the NOTs inside perfect here.
这些都会被PERFECT中的NOT给过滤掉
So it will throw out the ones which happened to be either mortal or fallible.
所以它会丢弃掉那些满足平凡的或者不可靠的数据
In the other order what happens
而对于另外一种顺序来说
is I set this up, started up with an empty frame.
我以一个空框架开始的
The perfect in here doesn't find anything for the NOTs to filter,
但是这里PERFECT没有可以给NOT过滤的东西
so nothing comes out here at all.
所以这里不会有什么输出
And there's sort of nothing there that gets fed into the address thing.
这也就导致没有东西输入到ADDRESS中
So here, I don't get an answer.
因此 我得不到答案
And again, the reason for that is NOT isn't generating anything.
在强调一下 这是因为NOT不会生成任何东西
NOT's only throwing out things.
NOT只会丢弃数据
And if I never started up with anything,
如果我不向NOT传递东西的话
there's nothing for it to throw out.
它也就不会输出
So out of this thing, I get the wrong answer.
这样我就得到了错误的答案
How can you fix that?
我们又该如何修复它呢？
Well, there are ways to fix that.
当然 有很多办法
So you might say, well, that's sort of stupid.
你可能认为 现在这样有点愚蠢
Why are you just doing all your NOT stuff at the beginning?
为什么要一开始就执行NOT呢？
The right way to implement NOT is to realize
想要正确地实现NOT
that when you have conditions like NOT,
就是要认识到当你遇到NOT时
you should generate all your answers first,
你应该首先生成好答案
and then with each of these dictionaries pass along
然后通过字典把它们传递过来
Gee, at the very end I'll do filtering.
然后再最后再做过滤
And there are implementations of logic languages that work like that
有些按照这种方式实现的逻辑式语言
that solve this particular problem.
能够解决这个问题
However, there's a more profound problem,
然而 还有一个更深刻的问题
which is which one of these is the right answer?
也就是 哪个才是正确答案呢？
Is it Mount Olympus or is it nothing?
是奥林匹斯山 还是没有呢？
So you might say it's Mount Olympus,
你可能会认为是奥林匹斯山
because after all, Zeus is in that database,
毕竟 宙斯在数据库中
and Zeus was neither mortal nor fallible.
宙斯不是平凡的 也不是不可靠的
So you might say Zeus wants to satisfy
因此你可能会认为宙斯满足
NOT mortal Zeus or NOT fallible Zeus.
(NOT (MORTAL ZEUS))或者(NOT (FALLIBLE ZEUS))
But let's actually look at that database.
但我们实际来看一看数据库
Let's look at it.
来看一下
There's no way-- how does it know that Zeus is not fallible?
它要如何知道宙斯不是不可靠的？
There's nothing in there about that.
这里面没有关于它的知识
What's in there is that humans are fallible.
里面只能得到人类是不可靠的
How does it know that Zeus is not mortal?
它又如何知道宙斯不是不可靠的呢？
There's nothing in there about that.
这其中没有相关的规则
It just said I don't have any rule, which--
它只是说 我没有这样的规则
see the only way I can deduce something's mortal is if it's human
我只能通过某人是人类来推断出他是平凡的
and that's all it really knows about mortal.
这也是它所知道关于“平凡”的所有东西
And in fact, if you remember your classical mythology,
然而 如果你还记得古典神话的话
you know that the Greek gods were not mortal but fallible.
你就知道 古希腊众神是不平凡的 但都不可靠
So the answer is not in the rules there.
所以 不能通过这些规则得到答案
See, why does it deduce that?
但它又为什么推导出这些呢？
See, Socrates would certainly not have made this error of logic.
显然 苏格拉底不会犯这类逻辑错误
What NOT means in this language is not NOT.
在这门语言中 NOT并不是NOT
It's not the NOT of logic.
不是逻辑非运算
What NOT needs in this language is
这门语言中 NOT表示的是
not deducible from things in the database
不可以从数据库中推断出结果
as opposed to not true.
而不是“非真”
That's a very big difference.
完全是天壤之别
Subtle, but big.
很细微 但也很巨大
So, in fact,
因此 实际上
this is perfectly happy to say not anything that it doesn't know about.
如果什么都不知道 最好就说NOT
So if you ask it is it not true
如果你问它
that Zeus likes chocolate ice cream?
宙斯是否喜欢巧克力冰激凌
It will say sure, it's not true.
它会说 这个查询当然非真
Or anything else or anything it doesn't know about.
这些事情它都不知道
NOT means not deducible from the things you've told me.
NOT表示：不能从你告知它的事实中推断出来
In a world where you're identifying not deducible
换句话说 你要把“无法推断出”
with, in fact, not true,
与“命题非真”区别开来
this is called the closed world assumption.
这被称作是“封闭世界假说”
closed world assumption.
封闭世界假说
Anything that I cannot deduce from what I know
只要结论不能通过我所知道的知识推断出来
is not true,
那么就不是真的
Right? If I don't know anything about x,
对吧 如果我对X一无所知
the x isn't true.
那么X就非真
That's very dangerous.
这相当危险
From a logical point of view,
首先 从逻辑学的角度来说
first of all, it doesn't really makes sense.
它一点也说不通
Because if I don't know anything about x,
因为如果我对X一无所知的话
I'm willing to say not x.
就说X非真
But am I willing to say not not x?
但为什么不说“X非真”非真
Well, sure, I don't know anything about that either maybe.
当然 我也许对后面那个命题也一无所知
So not not x is not necessarily the same as x
因此(NOT (NOT X))就没有必要与X一致
and so on and so on and so on, so
等等等等
there's some sort of funny bias in there.
因此 这里面一定有某种“偏见”
So that's sort of funny.
这相当有趣
The second thing,
第二点就是
if you start building up real reasoning programs based on this,
如果你基于此 构建一个真正的推理程序
think how dangerous that is.
想一想是多么地危险
You're saying I know I'm in a position
你说我知道我可以推断出
to deduce everything true that's relevant to this problem.
与这个问题有关的所有事情
I'm reasoning, and built into my reasoning mechanism
因为在我推理机制的内部
is the assumption that anything that I don't know
会认为所有与问题有关的知识
can't possibly be relevant to this problem.
我都已经知道了
Right? There are a lot of big organizations that work like that, right?
有相当多的大型组织都像这样运作 对吧？
Most corporate marketing divisions work like that.
大多数公司的市场部门都是这样工作的。
You know the consequences to that.
你们也知道这样做的后果
So it's very dangerous to start really
因此 向这个大型逻辑推理系统
typing in these big logical implication systems
输入各种查询 根据输出继续工作
and going on what they say,
的做法相当危险
because they have this really limiting assumption built in.
因为它们内建的假说非常地有限
So you have to be very, very careful about that.
因此你对此需要非常非常地小心
And that's a deep problem.
就是这么一个深层次问题
That's not a problem about
这个问题并不是
we can make a little bit cleverer implementation
通过构建更加聪明的实现
and do the filters and organize the
或者通过组织无穷循环
the infinite loops to make them go away.
以及过滤器就可以消除的
It's a different kind of problem.
这是完全不同的一类问题
It's a different semantics.
完全不同的语义
So I think to wrap this up, it's fair to say
我想该总结一下了 平心而论
that logic programming I think is a terrifically exciting idea,
逻辑式程序设计是一个振奋人心的想法
the idea that you can bridge this
这个想法使你能够弥合
gap from the imperative to the declarative,
命令式与声明式语言的鸿沟
that you can start talking about relations
使得你可以谈论关系
and really get tremendous power
从而获得惊人的力量
by going above the abstraction of what's my input and what's my output.
让你超越输入和输出的抽象
And linked to logic,
而关于逻辑
the problem is it's a goal that I think has yet to be realized.
我认为这个问题还尚未解决
And probably one of the very most interesting
也许现在语言中最令人感兴趣的
research questions going on now in languages
研究问题之一就是
is how do you somehow make a real logic language?
你该如何创建一门真正的逻辑语言？
And secondly, how do you bridge the gap
其次 你如何从
this world of logic and relations
这个逻辑和关系的世界
to the worlds of more traditional languages
到更传统语言的世界之间
and somehow combine the power of both.
架起桥梁并结合两者的力量
OK, let's break.
有什么问题吗？
AUDIENCE: Couldn't you solve that last problem
学生：你能够通过添加额外的规则
by having the extra rules that imply it?
来解决最后一个问题么？
The problem here is you have the definition of something,
这里的困境是：你有某物的定义
but you don't have the definition of its opposite.
但没有它对立面的定义
If you include in the database something that says
如果你在数据库中有
uh... something implies mortal x,
某些规则推导出(MORTAL X)
something else implies not mortal x,
另外一些规则推导出(NOT (MORTAL X))
haven't you basically solved the problem?
这不就基本上解决这个问题么？
PROFESSOR: But the issue is
教授：但问题就是
do you put a finite number of those in?
添加的这些规则是有穷个么？
AUDIENCE: If things are specified always in pairs--
学生：如果你同时定义正、反两面 --
PROFESSOR: But the question is then what do you do about deduction?
教授：但问题就是 你该如何去做推断？
See, you can't specify NOTs.
要知道 你不能直接定义命题的非
But the problem is, in a big system,
而问题就在于 在大型系统中
it turns out that might not be a finite number of things.
可能含有无穷个数的东西
There are also sort of two issues.
这其中有两个问题
Partly it might not be finite.
其一是可能有无穷项
Partly it might be that's not what you want.
另外是因为可能不向你想的那样
So a good example would be suppose I want to do connectivity.
一个极好的例子 就是连通性
I want a reason about connectivity.
我想对连通性做推理
And I'm going to tell you there's four things:
我会告诉你这有四个对象
a and b and c and d.
A、B、C和D
And I'll tell you a is connected to b
我会告诉你A和B相连
and c's connected to d.
C和D相连
And now I'll tell you is a connected to d?
然后我再告诉你A和D相连
That's the question.
就是这种情况
There's an example where I would like
在这个例子中
something like the closed world assumption.
我就希望有“封闭世界假说”这样的东西
That's a tiny toy,
这是个小玩具
but a lot of times, I want to be able to say something like
但是很多时候 我都想说
anything that I haven't told you, assume is not true.
我没告诉你的事 都假设非真
So it's not as simple as you only want to put in
所以这并不是你显式地
explicit NOTs all over the place.
为所有命题定义否命题就可以解决的
It's that sometimes it really isn't clear what you even want.
而是有些时候 你不清楚自己真正想要什么
That having to specify both everything and not everything is too precise,
同时定义原命题与否命题又太过于精细
and then you get down into problems there.
这会使你陷入困境
But there are a lot of approaches that
但还是有很多方法
you know, that explicitly put in NOTs and reason based on that.
显式地定义否命题 并基于此进行推理
So it's a very good idea.
这个想法非常好
It's just that then it starts becoming a little cumbersome
只是在一些复杂的大型问题中
in the very large problems you'd like to use.
这么做就变得有些笨重了
AUDIENCE: I'm not sure how directly related to the argument this is,
学生：有个论点 我不知道它和本节课的直接关系
but one of your points was that
但你想要表达的是
one of the dangers of the closed world rule is
封闭世界假说的危害之一就是
you never really know all the things that are there.
你永远不会真正了解那里的所有事物
You never really know all the parts to it.
你永远不会知道它们的每个部分
Isn't that a major problem with any programming?
这难道不是任何一门程序设计语言的主要问题吗？
I always write programs where I
写程序时 我总是
I assume that I've got all the cases,
假设我考虑了所有的情况
and so I check for them all or whatever, and i
然后我检查了每一种情况
and somewhere down the road, I
然而在某处
I find out that I didn't check for one of them.
我发现了我遗漏了其中的一个
PROFESSOR: Well, sure, it's true.
教授：你说得很对
But the problem here is
但这里的问题在于
it's that assumption which is the thing that you're making
对于你所做的事情
if you believe you're identifying this with logic.
你是否认为它是逻辑问题
So you're quite right.
你说得非常正确
It's a situation you're never in.
这是你永远不会遇到的情况
The problem is if you're starting to believe that
问题在于 如果你认为
what this is doing is logic
你在进行逻辑式程序设计
and you look at the rules you write down
然后审视你所编写的规则
and say what can I deduce from them,
并思考能从中推断出什么
you have to be very careful to remember that NOT means something else.
你就需要清醒地认识到NOT具有另外的意义
And it means something else based on an assumption
它的意义基于某种假设
which is probably not true.
并且可能并不正确
AUDIENCE: Do I understand you correctly that
学生：我不知道这样理解是否正确
you cannot fix this problem
也就是我们无法通过改变NOT
without killing off all possibilities of inference through altering NOT?
来消灭推断的所有可能性 从而解决这个问题？
PROFESSOR: No, that's not quite right.
教授：不 并不是这样
There are ways to do logic with real NOTs.
有很多种方法可以实现真正的逻辑非
There are actually ways to do that.
实际上有很多种方法
But they're very inefficient as far as anybody knows.
但目前没有一个广为人知的高效算法
And they're much more--
而且他们还--
they don't--  the, quote, inference in here
这里所谓的“推论”
is built into this unifier
是建立在这个合一算法
and this pattern matching unification algorithm.
以及模式匹配算法之中的
There are ways to automate real logical reasoning.
有多种方法可以实现真正的逻辑推理
But it's not based on that,
但它们并不基于此
and logic programming languages don't tend to do that
而逻辑式程序设计语言也不倾向于这么做
because it's very inefficient as far as anybody knows.
因为大家都知道 那样做非常低效
All right, thank you.
好吧 下课
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/DeathKing/Learning-SICP